# 大米 小米 鸡头米 江米 高粱米
Rice, millet, gorgon fruit, jiang glutinous rice, sorghum
# 花生米 红小豆 绿豆 红芸豆
Peanuts, red beans, mung beans, red kidney beans
# 白芸豆 桂圆 莲子 小枣儿
White kidney beans, dried longan fruit, lotus seeds, small dates
# 核桃仁 南瓜子 藜麦 栗子
Walnut, pumpkin seed, quinoa, chestnut
# 葡萄干 碱面
Raisin, dietary alkali
# 酒店版的八宝粥
Hotel-version Laba Congee
# 一定要黏黏糊糊的
Must be glutinous and slimy
# 红小豆 绿豆 红芸豆
Red beans, mung beans, and red kidney beans
# 这都提前泡
They should be soaked ahead of time
# 这个时候我们稍微捏一点碱
Now we pinch a little dietary alkali
# 不要太多 多了就该苦了
Not too much, cuz too much will turn it bitter
# 熬这粥呢
Making this congee
# 我需要一锅粥的时候
When I need a pot of congee,
# 我这水不能马上兑到一锅水
I shouldn’t fill the pot with water at the beginning.
# 这样这豆就不爱烂
Because that would make it hard to cook through the beans.
# 一边煮一边点凉水
Instead, I am boiling it while adding some cold water
# 得点那么三回 四回 五回
I am adding water 3, 4, and 5 times
# 就是一冷一热一激它
To irritate it with alternating hotness and coldness
# 这豆很快就开花了
The beans would soon be cooked through (“blossom”).
# 这是第一环节先煮着
This is the first step. Let’s cook it on the side.
# 这芸豆是最不爱烂的
The kidney beans is the least easy to get cooked through.
# 做这个东西要有点层次感
If we want to enrich the depth of the congee,
# 就是分头单独给它压一下
We should pressure-cook the beans alone
# 大约得压将近10分钟
Which would take about 10 minutes
# 这个只要一开锅就点水
Add cold water as soon as the pot is boiled.
# 好 浇水 点
Ok, add cold water.
# 这火尽量别开的太大
Don’t turn on the heat too much.
# 让它慢慢开
Let the pot slowly boiled.
# 二伯给盖上
Put on a lid, Er Bai.
# 过了腊八就是节
The Spring Festival comes right after Laba Festival.
# 初九初十就开始准备年夜饭了
On the 9th and 10th of the Lunar Year, people start to prepare the meal for the Spring Festival Eve.
# 家里什么扫房子的
Clean up the home
# 搞卫生的 洗衣服的
Sanitize. Wash clothes.
# 这些准备工作都要有了
People are starting to do these preparation work.
# 看着啊
Look.
# 点水 鸡头米放进去
Add cold water, then the gorgon fruit.
# 因为它也不爱烂
Because it is also hard to cook through.
# 把枣放进去
Add the small dates.
# 还有藜麦
And quinoa.
# 这都是不爱烂的就早点放
Add these ingredients that are hard to cook through
# 我再把这个栗子给它处理一下
Let me prep the chestnut.
# 栗子得剥皮
First peel the skin.
# 把那头必须得切了 它好剥呀
Cut off that end so it is easy to peel.
# 好多人忽视了这个
Many people would miss that.
# 这个碱面 其实这个碱面
The dietary alkali. Actually this alkali…
# 如果说要放在粥里边
Adding the alkali to the congee
# 它起的黏性东西特别好
Would make the congee glutinous and slimy.
# 二伯 劳驾 是不是大爷
Er Bai, please comment. Da Ye, am I right?
# 在农村要是熬粥啊
In the rural village, people always cook congee
# 都搁碱 出来特别好吃
With alkali, which makes it extra tasty
# 你要熬什么大棒碴粥 你必须得搁
Like, to make Da Bang Cha Congee (similar to Polenta), you have to add alkali.
# 你看这绿豆 红小豆
Take a look at the mung beans, red beans
# 有张嘴的了
They are starting to open up
# 一个是拿凉水激的
One reason is the cold water
# 还有一个是碱面
Another is the alkali
# 这时候我们把花生米给下了
At this moment we add the peanuts
# 花米煮完了以后是脆的
The peanuts would become crispy after cooking
# 这个高粱米给下了
Add the sorghum
# 高粱米不乱汤是吧
The soghum won’t mess up the congee right?
# 不乱汤 放棒子碴就不爱乱汤
No it won’t as long as you are adding the grounded dried corns
# 要放棒子面就麻烦’
Not the corn starch
# 火呢别太大 慢慢（熬）
Keep the heat low. Slowly cook it.
# 其实做饭是一种享受
In fact, cooking is enjoyable.
# 尤其像咱老母亲
Like, my mom
# 她一说明天过腊八了
she would wake up early tomorrow
# 她老早就起来了
For it is Laba Festival
# 你看一代一代就这么过来的
Generations of parents have been following such tradition.
# 比如说为什么要做这腊八粥
For example, why making this Laba Congee?
# 让我们学会感恩
Because we need to learn to be grateful.
# 大爷 是不是这么个意思 没错
Da Ye, am I right? Yes.
# 这个栗子 只要开锅
The chestnut, as soon as the pot is boiling…
# 这皮一软 就ok
And the skin is soft, it is ok.
# 这莲子呢 很重要
The lotus seed is very important.
# 你看这个芯
Look at the core.
# 一捅 这个晾干了
Poke it out and dry it up.
# 送到药房 高价收购
Send it to the Chinese medicine pharmacy and you will get a high monetary return.
# 搁二伯这茶杯里
(Or) put it in Er Bai’s tea cup.
# 莲子放进去了
Lotus seed is in.
# 咱们开始剥栗子
Now let’s peel chestnut.
# 这个栗子煮啊 只要一开锅
The chestnut should be cooked to boiling
# 皮一软 大约5分钟就好了
Once the skin is soft, take about 5 more minutes.
# 下芸豆
Add kidney beans.
# 好了 栗子放进去了
Ok the chestnut is added.
# 所有的东西都差不多了
All the things are pretty much ready.
# 开始放米了
Add rice now.
# 江米 桂圆
Jiang glutinuous rice, dried longan fruit
# 大米 小米
Rice, millet
# 这时候就全搁下去了
Now add all of then
# 要分期分批的把这些原料
Add these ingredients one set by one
# 通过不同的加工手法
With different processing methods.
# 投入到腊八粥 喝的时候
Add some to Laba Congee. When having the congee
# 粥黏 又香 比较有层次感
Sticky, fragrant, and a sense of depth
# 让它开锅 让它翻滚
Wait till the congee is boiled
# 那东西一沉底儿就容易扒锅
If the congee gets too thick and the ingredients sink, it would get dried up and stick to the bottom
# 就容易糊锅
And eventually get charred.
# 这快好了
It’s almost ready.
# 我感受到了 熬这个粥
I feel that, cooking this congee
# 真是用 用心在熬
Is to put your heart and soul into this.
# 心很重要
This is very important.
# 每个地儿都要达到精彩
Every corner has to be exquisite.
# 一定要黏黏糊糊的
Must be glutinous and slimy.
# 这时候我们这粥差不多了
Our congee is almost ready.
# 来点瓜子仁
Add some pumpkin seed
# 瓜子仁 可多可少
Pumpkin seeds could be more or less
# 葡萄干
Raisin
# 咱们找一碗 一会儿啊
Let’s find a bowl.
# 那时候父母在家 尤其是母亲
At that moment, the parents are home, especially mom
# 起一大早等你起床的时候
She would wake up early, and when you wake up
# 不管几点起 就是七点起床的时候
No matter when, like 7 o’ clock.
# 那粥都给你熬好了
She would have the congeed ready for you.
# 这就是父母用心的那种爱
This is the type of love from parents.
# 其实我们要做的什么
What we should actually be doing,
# 就继承这种 是吧
Is to inherit such tradition
# 把这种爱的传统给延伸下去
Of love.
# 延伸到后一代
Pass it on to the next generation
# 我就记着我小时候
I remember when I was a kid,
# 这一年到头喝的都是稀粥
I grow up drinking gruel (thin congee) all year long.
# 只有到腊八了
Only when Laba Festival comes,
# 家里边还能喝一回糨粥
We could afford to have a richer congee.
# 比吃肉香
It is better than having meat.
# 吃了这么多年的腊八粥
Years of having Laba congee.
# 今天我算见识到了高配版
I finally see a high-end version.
# 要是我在家里边 就像我这个岁数
If I am at home, in my age,
# 我也是一下全把搁进去
I would also add everything in at once.
# 搁里边熬着去了
So they are cooked together.
# 熬那个腊八粥不是这样熬
But Laba Congee should not be made like that.
# 熬粥是分步骤 分层次
There are steps for cooking congee to create a sense of depth.
# 一步一步的去做的
Step by step.
# 因为今天这粥从始至终我看了
I got that because I was watching the cooking process from the beginning to the end.
# 大爷一直走在锅边
I saw Da Ye sitting by the pot the whole time.
# 这就是咱老一辈人
This is our older generation
# 咱们的前辈
Our senior
# 就是说人家做事的一个态度
I am appreciating their persistent attitudes in doing things
# 你看简简单单一个粥都是如此
Even in cooking congee
# 何况说做其他的菜
Let alone other dishes
# 希望我们在家里边熬个粥
I hope that whenever we cook Laba congee at home
# 一定 像我们过去
Must, like the previous generations
# 老母亲呀 妈妈呀
mathers
# 起个大早
Wake up early
# 熬那锅粥 那是带有亲情的
Cook the pot of congee with family love
# 今天咱们在老饭骨呈现腊八粥
Today we present Laba congee in our Laofangu Channel
# 就是让我们这些网友粉丝们
Is to show our internet fans
# 让我们更多的年轻人
And our young generations
# 腊八吃什么
What to eat on Laba Festival
# 不是光吃腊八蒜
Not just Laba garlic
# 还有一碗腊八粥
But also a bowl of Laba Congee
# 希望大家喜欢
Hope everyone like it!